<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Faithful account of the renewed persecution of the churches of Lower Aquitaine in France in the year 1692 to which is prefixed a parallel between the ancient and new persecutors, or the portraicture of Lewis XIV in some of his cruelties and barbarities : with some reflections upon the unreasonable fondness of a certain party amongst us, for the French king.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40765</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F263</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31494</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12026786</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12026786</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52644</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40765)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52644)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1009:37)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Faithful account of the renewed persecution of the churches of Lower Aquitaine in France in the year 1692 to which is prefixed a parallel between the ancient and new persecutors, or the portraicture of Lewis XIV in some of his cruelties and barbarities : with some reflections upon the unreasonable fondness of a certain party amongst us, for the French king.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Louis --  XIV, --  King of France, 1638-1715.</term>
               <term>France --  Church history.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52644:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A FAITHFUL ACCOUNT OF The Renewed Perſecution OF THE CHURCHES OF Lower Aquitaine in France.</p>
            <p>In the YEAR 1692.</p>
            <p>To which is prefixed, A Parallel between the Ancient and New Perſecutors; or the Portraicture of <hi>LEWIS</hi> XIV. in ſome of his Cruelties and Barbarities.</p>
            <p>With ſome Reflections upon the unreaſonable Fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a certain Party amongſt us, for the <hi>French</hi> King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin</hi> near the <hi>Oxford-Arms,</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane.</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:52644:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52644:2"/>
            <head>A PARALLEL Between the Ancient and New Perſecutors, OR THE Portraicture of <hi>LEWIS</hi> XIV. In ſome of his CRUELTIES and BARBARITIES.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>IT was in the heat of the Perſecution of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Churches of <hi>France,</hi> that I firſt read <hi>Lactantius</hi>'s Relation of the Death of the Primitive Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. The Cruelties practiſed in his Age upon the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and revived in ours with ſo much inhuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity upon our Brethren in <hi>France,</hi> put me upon the thoughts of making a Parallel between the <hi>Ancient</hi> Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſpeaks of, and our worſe <hi>Modern</hi> ones under <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. And indeed I was the more tempted to it, by the great likeneſs I found there was between them and the <hi>French</hi> King's Cruel Inſtruments; but having read over the ingenious Preface to that Book, written by the now Learned Biſhop of <hi>Sarum,</hi> I then altered my Deſign, becauſe I thought ſuch a Parallel was ſufficiently done already, very conciſely in that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52644:3"/>Preface. And I had continued ſtill in the ſame mind, but that an Account of the new Barbarities committed in <hi>France,</hi> upon the Proteſtants of the <hi>Lower Aquitaine,</hi> being come to my hand, and being ſo earneſtly ſolicited to publiſh it, I think it will not be amiſs to prefix to it a much larger Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon between thoſe Tyrants, that we may ſee how like the <hi>French</hi> King is to the Ancient Perſecutors, and that he follows their ſteps not only in the Perſecution, but alſo in all their other Vices, if he does not far exceed them. I have been ſo much the more induced to this, by the ſtrange pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of a certain Party amongſt us, who yet pretending to be Proteſtants, are yet nevertheleſs eager to fall down and Worſhip the Golden Image of ſuch a <hi>Monſter</hi> as this, and forgetting what they owe to their God, to Their Majeſties, under whom they lead quiet and peaceable Lives, and to their Country, are fond of having for their King, the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Mankind, the Invader of the Liberties of <hi>Europe,</hi> and the greateſt Perſecutor of the Chriſtian Religion that ever was in the World. I intend in the firſt place to ſet the Characters <hi>Lactantius</hi> gives of the Perſecutors of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, with the Method they made uſe of in their Perſecution, and afterwards I'll ſhew that thoſe Characters do perfectly agree with the <hi>French</hi> King, and that he has taken the very ſame Meaſures to deſtroy the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in his Kingdom, as the former took to aboliſh it in the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire. But becauſe the World tends always to a greater perfection; I'll ſhew alſo that this <hi>French</hi> King has exceeded <hi>Maximian, Valerian,</hi> and other Perſecutors in Barbarity.</p>
               <p>The Characters <hi>Lactantius</hi> gives of his Perſecutors, are theſe; 1. <hi>That they were addicted to the Brutalities of ſeveral Pleaſures.</hi> 2. <hi>That they ruined their Subjects by ſevere Impoſitions, and heavy Taxes for maintaining vaſt Armies.</hi> 3. <hi>That they ſhewed in their Wars ſome Puſilanimity, or at leaſt more care than was decent for preſerving themſelves from all danger.</hi> 4. <hi>That they were ſo weak as to be fondly pleaſed with the moſt exceſſive Flatteries could be made them, and aſſumed undeſervedly the moſt glorious Titles, even ſome to Blaſphemy it ſelf.</hi> 5. <hi>That they were
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52644:3"/>profuſe in the raiſing of coſtly Buildings.</hi> 6. <hi>That they were ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful for many Years together in their undertakings.</hi> And Laſtly, <hi>That they had Fearful, Superſtitious, and Cruel Tempers.</hi> Theſe are the Characters of thoſe Ancient Perſecutors: I muſt obſerve now what was the pretence of their perſecutions, and the method they made uſe of to compaſs their horrid deſign.</p>
               <p>What the pretence of their Perſecutions was, we may read in an <hi>Edict</hi> of <hi>Maximian</hi> himſelf quoted by <hi>Lactantius</hi> and <hi>Evſebius</hi> in his Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, <hi>Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. in which 'tis ſaid, <hi>That the Chriſtians having forſaken the Religion of their Forefathers, and framed new Laws to govern themſelves by, the Emperors thought themſelves obliged to Publiſh their</hi> Edicts <hi>to force them to return to their firſt Inſtitutions.</hi> The meaſures they took to compaſs their Deſign were theſe: 1. They pulled down the Chriſtian Churches. 2. They declared the Chriſtians incapable of all Honours, Truſts, or Offices, either Civil or Military. 3. They put them out of the protection of the Law, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that they could not ſue for any injuries done them. 4. Afterwards they commanded all the Chriſtians to abjure their Religion. 5. But ſeeing that they ſtood firm to their Rules, they practiſed all the Cruelties imaginable upon them. <hi>6thly.</hi> and <hi>Laſtly.</hi> All the Books of the Sacred Scripture, they could find, were burnt by their Orders. Having thus obſerved the Characters of thoſe <hi>Primitive Perſecutors;</hi> the pretence of their Perſecution, and the method they made uſe of to deſtroy the Chriſtian Religion, I muſt give you now a plain <hi>Idea</hi> of this <hi>French</hi> King, and ſhew what has been his pretence in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting, with ſo much Inhumanity, his Proteſtant Subjects; and what meaſures he has taken to aboliſh the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in his Kingdom.</p>
               <p n="1">1. I think it will be very needleſs to ſhew, how that the <hi>French</hi> King has delivered himſelf up to the Brutalities of ſenſual Pleaſures; For who is unacquainted with his many Adulteries? Aud who has not heard of the famous Ladies, <hi>La Valiere, Fontange,</hi> and <hi>Monteſpan,</hi> and of the many Children he has got by them? But I cannot paſs over this Subject without obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, That the Lady <hi>Monteſpan</hi> being Married to a Noble
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52644:4"/>
                  <hi>French</hi> man, and the <hi>French</hi> King Married too, he has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the blackeſt of all Adulteries. I do not read in Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that thoſe Monſters <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſpeaks of, have been guilty of ſuch a Crime as this: But ſuppoſing they had, they were leſs Criminal than the <hi>French</hi> King, becauſe they could plead in their defence the examples of their Gods: Whereas <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth. cannot have ſuch an excuſe, living under the ſeeming Profeſſion of a Chriſtian Religion; which though very much corrupted, yet informs him, that Adultery is one of the horridſt Crimes in the ſight of God; and that it is in expreſs terms forbidden in his Law. I hope this is enough, without being obliged to ſpeak of the Lady <hi>Maintenon,</hi> ſome believing that ſhe is really his Wife.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I am next to prove, That the <hi>Fremch</hi> King has ruined his Subjects by Severe Impoſitions, and heavy Taxes for maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his vaſt Armies; and this I can make out with as much eaſe, as I have done his Vices. Though <hi>Charles</hi> the great was Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror of <hi>Germany,</hi> King of <hi>Italy,</hi> and of <hi>France,</hi> yet he never maintained in time of Peace near Four hundred thouſand men, as this <hi>French</hi> King has done. Every body knows how vaſt a charge ſuch an Army muſt needs be to the <hi>French</hi> People; for their King having not as yet (as ever I heard of) found the Philoſopher's Stone, 'tis their <hi>Blood, and the ſweat of their Brows,</hi> I mean, their Money, that muſt maintain this prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Number of Soldiers, the Tools uſed for their Slavery, and the unconfined Ambition of their Prince. The bare Liſt of the Taxes impoſed upon them by this preſent King, is enough to make a Volume, therefore I muſt forbear a particular Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of them; but to give you a true Idea of the number and heavineſs of thoſe Impoſitions, Let me only obſerve to you, what was the Annual Revenue of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIth. who ſufficiently invaded the Liberties of his People; and that of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIIIth. and afterwards we ſhall ſee what that of the preſent <hi>French</hi> King amounts to. The Annual Revenue of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIth. was Four millions, and Seven hundred thouſand Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; but that Sum being found too heavy upon the Nation, in his Son King <hi>Charles</hi> the VIIIth. his Reign, his Revenue at the deſire of the States of Parliament Aſſembled at <hi>Tours,</hi> was
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52644:4"/>reduced to Two millions, five hundred thouſand Livers. But ſince that time the Revenues of the Kings of <hi>France</hi> have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digiouſly increaſed, as thoſe Prince's inſatiable thirſt after the Slavery of their People, inſomuch that the late King <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIIIth. his Revenue amounted to Five and fifty millions of Livers. But that Sum being then thought, with a great deal of Reaſon, to be highly exorbitant, the <hi>French</hi> Nation com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained very much of the hard uſage they received from their King: But what would they give now to have ſuch a one, ſince even his Exorbitance was tolerable, nay, eaſy and gentle, in compariſon with that of their preſent Oppreſſor? For as the world is ſaid to refine every day upon us, and much to exceed the Ancient; ſo this <hi>French</hi> King, finding ſuch a Sum too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle for his vaſt Projects and Deſigns, hath, through a moſt tranſcendent refinedneſs in Politicks, contrived a thouſand ways to drain his Peoples Purſes, and hath attained to ſuch a ſingular and maſterly perfection in this Art, that now his Annual Revenue, according to the ſtate of the Royal Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, Amounts to near a <hi>Hundred and fifty millions.</hi> And if we take into conſideration this prodigious Sum, together with what comes to the Clergy, we ſhall not be ſurprized at the miſerable condition of the <hi>French</hi> Nation (eſpecially in this time of War) for want of Trade.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I hope the <hi>French</hi> King is very like to the Perſecutors of <hi>Lactantius,</hi> as to the two preceding Characters. Let us ſee now if he comes ſhort of them in the Third, <hi>viz.</hi> In <hi>want of Courage, or at leaſt in ſhewing more care than is decent to preſerve himſelf from all danger.</hi> I muſt confeſs, the Parallel is not very exact in this particular, for this <hi>French</hi> King goes beyond them all in Baſeneſs, and downright Cowardice. I read in the <hi>Roman</hi> Hiſtory, that <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> though Vicious, and a Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, ſhewed nevertheleſs ſome Courage in a Battel againſt <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinus</hi> his Competitor; and in reducing <hi>Aquileus</hi> one of his Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, who had cauſed himſelf to be Proclaimed Emperor in in <hi>Egypt.</hi> That <hi>Maximian,</hi> ſirnamed the <hi>Herculian,</hi> has been preſent in ſeveral Battels and Rencounters; and that <hi>Galerius Maximian</hi> routed <hi>Narſeus</hi> King of the <hi>Perſians</hi> in a Bloody Battel in <hi>Armenia.</hi> And yet notwithſtanding thoſe Actions,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52644:5"/>if they have been taxed with Baſeneſs and Puſillanimity by <hi>Lactantius,</hi> and other Writers, What muſt we ſay of the <hi>French</hi> King? He that never had the Courage to Command his Army in a day of Battel, and who has never Beſieged any Town, till after he had made the Bargain ſure for it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. I have ſaid, That <hi>the Primitive Perſecutors were ſo weak, as to be fondly pleaſed with the moſt exceſſive flatteries could be made them, and aſſumed undeſervedly the moſt Glorious Titles, even ſome to Blaſphemy it ſelf.</hi> And I am to prove in this place, that the <hi>French</hi> King will by no means be inferior to them in this point, no more than in the former. He has aſſumed the Title of <hi>Great,</hi> which never man before him did in his own life time; he has taken the <hi>Sun</hi> for his Emblem, with this proud Motto, <hi>nec plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus impar,</hi> to ſignify that he is the <hi>Phaeniz</hi> of the world, and truly he is in the right on't, not however in his opinion, but only in mine: For I ſteadfaſtly believe there is not a man in the world that can equal him in ſo many bad qualities. He has ſuffered his Statue to be ſet up in publick Places, and to be harangued by <hi>Academies,</hi> and <hi>Corps de ville,</hi> which is their Common Council, and to be repreſented as Lording it over the Earth and the Sea. But the moſt Blaſphemous of all, is that of the place called <hi>des Victoirs,</hi> where one may ſee him crowned by Victory, trampling <hi>Hereſy</hi> under his feet, and the Four Parts of the Earth repreſented by Four Slaves, chain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the <hi>Pedaſtal,</hi> with this impious Motto, VIRO IM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MORTALI, <hi>the Immortal Man.</hi> This has been thought ſo Blaſphemous, even to Father <hi>Meneſtrier,</hi> tho a moſt egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Flatterer himſelf, that in his Hiſtory of this <hi>French</hi> King by the Medals, he has been aſhamed to relate this <hi>Motto</hi> in the deſcription he gives of that place. I could quote a Thouſand other inſtances of this nature, but I muſt forbear, for fear of being too tedious: However, I hope the Reader will not take it amis if I ſhew him how <hi>Monſieur Peliſſon</hi> (one of the <hi>Academy</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi>) ſpeaks of his Maſter in a Panegyrick pronounced by him, and which is Printed in the laſt Edition of the Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of that <hi>Academy. Antiquity,</hi> ſays he, <hi>had a great and noble reward in ſtore for Heroes, viz. their</hi> Apotheoſis, <hi>or Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of them into the number of the Gods. At the Funeral of one
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52644:5"/>of the greateſt of their Emperors, there was one of the</hi> Patrician <hi>Family, who Swore, That he ſaw the Emperors Soul fly up to Heaven in a moſt ſplendid Triumph. The ſame Ancients imagined, That the Souls or</hi> Genii <hi>of theſe Heroes did overſee and influence the great Actions here below, and were of the ſwifteſt agility in going about this their charge: But ſure I am, if ever any Prince deſerved ſuch an Apotheoſis,</hi> or <hi>Tranſlation into the Number of the Gods, our Invincible and Auguſt Monarch merits it in a tranſcendent degree; all his actions are Godlike, and his influence on the whole Affairs of</hi> Europe <hi>are ſo univerſal, that he ſeems to participate of the Nature and Power of that</hi> Univerſal Intelligence <hi>that rules all ſublunary things:</hi> Such expreſſions are certainly impious, but yet they are very modeſt in compariſon of theſe which follow a little after in the ſame <hi>Panegyrick. If theſe Pagans, who fondly would have ſacrificed to the Two Apoſtles, and ſaid of them,</hi> the Gods are come down among us, <hi>had been the eye witneſſes of the mighty Actions of</hi> Lewis le Grand, <hi>which contain ſo many Lineaments of a Deity, they would have had more reaſon to have erected Altars to this Divinity of</hi> France, <hi>than to all thoſe of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity.</hi> If this be not Blaſphemy, I am then to learn where it may be found, or what it is that we call Impiety: And ſure I am, that <hi>Diocletian</hi> himſelf was not ſo guilty in aſſuming the Title of <hi>God;</hi> ſince he had the examples of <hi>Caligula</hi> and <hi>Domitian,</hi> to juſtifie him in that ſhameful piece of vanity, by the like in thoſe his Two Predeceſſors: 'Tis ſaid alſo of that Heathen Prince, that to appear more <hi>like God</hi> to the People, he was wont to wear a Suit ſet thick with Precious Stones; And has not this vanity too been imitated by the preſent <hi>French</hi> King when he gave Audience to the Ambaſſadors of <hi>Siam?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſays, That the <hi>Primitive Perſecutors were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe in the raiſing of coſtly Buildings,</hi> and ſo is this <hi>French</hi> King. That ingenious Writer obſerveth, That <hi>Diocletian</hi> laid many Taxes on ſeveral Provinces, to build in <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>media</hi> fine Palaces for himſelf, for his Wife, and for his Daughters, and an <hi>Hippodrome,</hi> an <hi>Arſenal,</hi> and a <hi>Mint-houſe:</hi> But what were thoſe Buildings in compariſon with thoſe of this <hi>French</hi> King, if we conſider that the very Lead
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52644:6"/>alone imployed at <hi>Verſailles,</hi> coſt near<note n="*" place="margin">Above Two Millions Ster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</note> Thirty Millions? He obſerveth alſo, That no ſooner were thoſe Buildings finiſhed, but he found ſome fault or other in them, and then he cauſed them to be all pulled down again, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>build after another manner, according to a new Caprice that came in his head, though even then they were not ſecured from other Alterations. And is not this a lively Picture of the madneſs of this <hi>French</hi> King? Have not the <hi>Louvre, Verſailles</hi> and <hi>Triennon,</hi> been built and pulled down, and afterwards rebuilt, and then levelled with the ground ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times over? So like is <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth. to that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Perſecutor. I have done with this Subject when I have related a paſſage which proveth how profuſe the <hi>French</hi> King hath been for the beautifying his Palaces. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal made to him for this <hi>Machine</hi> which draws the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the River <hi>Seine</hi> near <hi>Marly,</hi> to the Water-ſpouts of <hi>Verſailles;</hi> was looked upon at firſt as that made formerly to <hi>Alexander</hi> about Mount <hi>Athos,</hi> not however ſo much for the difficulty of that Machine, as for the prodigious Sums of Money which were demanded to bring it to its perfection; and therupon his Wiſe Councellors endeavoured to diſſwade him from ſo coſtly a deſign; but he asked them, Whether they believ'd the thing was poſſible? And upon their Anſwering, That they thought it might be ſo in it ſelf, but not in the circumſtances his <hi>Exchequer</hi> was in; <hi>Well then,</hi> ſaid the King, <hi>ſince that Machine is poſſible, I will have it, and it ſhall be done, if there be any Money in</hi> France.<note n="*" place="margin">It coſt at firſt above 6000 <hi>l.</hi> and ſince above 15000. every Year.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Lactantius</hi> obſerveth, That the <hi>Primitive Perſecutors were ſucceſsful for many Years together, but their end was deplorable:</hi> Upon which, though I do not pretend to determine what will be the End of this <hi>French</hi> King, yet I ſay, he is ſo like thoſe Ancient Monſters, as well in his Succeſſes, as in all the other preceding Characters, that it will not be ſo impertinent as it may ſeem at firſt, to believe that the Exit of his Impious Life may be in a very Tragical manner, as well as theirs were, who were the Primitive Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors. That he has been ſucceſeful for theſe many Years,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52644:6"/>I think no body can deny; and if we but caſt our eyes upon his prodigious Conqueſts, we muſt confeſs, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the circumſtances of the preſent times, they are more conſiderable, than thoſe of the <hi>Perſecutors</hi> we ſpeak of: All things have ſmiled upon him near theſe Thirty years laſt, and 'tis upon that account his Flatterers have ſaid, that he is the Sovereign diſpoſer of the Fate of the World.</p>
               <p n="7">7. I come now to the laſt Character <hi>Lactantius</hi> gives of his Perſecutors, <hi>viz. That they had Fearful, Superſtitious, and Cruel Tempers;</hi> and I am to ſhew that this <hi>French</hi> King is of the like Complexion too: But having already proved that he wants Courage, I have at the ſame time ſhewed how Fearful his Temper was, and how little he deſerved the Title of a Warlike Prince. As to his Superſtition, I hope I need not to ſay any thing upon that Topick, for who is ignorant of it? Truly he muſt be Superſtitious to the laſt degree, and wholly unacquainted with God's Mercy, who believes or hopes to obtain the forgiveneſs of his many repeated Adulteries, and other Sins, by committing new Crimes under the falſe pretences of Converting <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</hi> Though <hi>Nero, Domitian,</hi> and <hi>Maximian</hi> have been ſo Cruel, that it ſeems their Succeſſors muſt yield to them in Inhumanity; yet here is a new Competiter who is like to win the prize from them all: This Rival is <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>XIVth.</hi> for if we compare his Cruelties (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exagerating the matter in the leaſt) with thoſe of the <hi>Primitive Perſecutors,</hi> we ſhall find that he is far ſuperior to them. I muſt ſet aſide at preſent the Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties practiſed under pretence of Religion, to conſider of thoſe committed upon other accounts. Indeed I read in Hiſtory, That thoſe execrable Monſters put to Death a great many of their Subjects upon frivolous pretences, and that one of them had a mind to ſet <hi>Rome</hi> on Fire; but I do not find any Tracts of their Inhumanity ſo frightful as the Rubbiſh and Aſhes of <hi>Frankendal, Manh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Spire,</hi> and <hi>Worms.</hi> But perhaps it will be objected, That this is not a good proof of this <hi>French</hi> King's Cruelties, for thoſe Places be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52644:7"/>to his Enemies, the Military Law allows ſuch ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Treatment. To this I Anſwer, That the Military Law allows no ſuch Actions among Chriſtians, nor has it ever been allowed to deſtroy a Country by Fire and Sword in that Inhuman manner this <hi>French</hi> King has deſtroyed the <hi>Palatinate;</hi> where ſo many People of all Ages and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have been Murthered; where ſo many Towns have been Plundered and Burnt, notwithſtanding the Words and Aſſurances given them by the <hi>Dolphin</hi> himſelf at their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulations; and where ſo many fine Churches and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Houſes, as well as the Prince's Palaces have been deſtroyed, and levelled with the ground, and all this almoſt without any Declaration of War.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>What I have ſaid is ſufficient, I hope, to make a true Parallel between the Perſecutors of the Primitive Church, and one of this Age, and to convince all the world, that there is an extream likeneſs betwixt them. I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now proceed to inquire, into what have been the <hi>French</hi> King's pretences to this Bloody Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Proteſtants of his own Countrey. I have already ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in the beginning of this Parallel, That the firſt <hi>Chriſtians were Perſecuted under pretence that they had forſaken the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of their forefathers, and framed new Aſſemblies, and new Laws; whereby the Emperors had been forc'd to publiſh their Edicts, to oblige them to return to their firſt Inſtitutions:</hi> And I muſt deſire you to obſerve here, That 'tis upon the very ſame account that the <hi>French Hugonots</hi> have been ſo Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly Perſecuted in our Days. Are we not accuſed for having forſaken the Religion of our fore-fathers, and to have rejected the precepts of our dear <hi>Mother</hi> the Church? Are we not charged with having framed new Laws, and new Aſſemblies to govern our ſelves by, and to break the Union of the Church? And is it not upon this account that the Tyrant of <hi>France</hi> has Publiſh'd likewiſe his <hi>Edicts</hi> to oblige the Proteſtants of his Kingdom, to return to their <hi>firſt Inſtitutions;</hi> that is to ſay, to the Profeſſion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Religion, from which he ſuppoſed they were wilfully, and without any ground, ſeparated?
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52644:7"/>But let us hear what the <hi>French</hi> King ſays himſelf in the Preface of that famous <hi>Edict</hi> given in <hi>October</hi> 1685. to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal that of <hi>Nants.</hi> He ſays, That <hi>Henry</hi> the IV. his Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father had no other deſign in putting forth the Edict, called <hi>de Nantes,</hi> than to leſſen the <hi>Averſion</hi> which was between the Proteſtants and the Catholicks, to be thereby enabled to effect more ſucceſsfully the Reunion of the ſaid Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> from which they had depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon ſuch ſlight pretences. That his Father <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. had the ſame deſign, and that he himſelf ſince his coming to the Throne, had endeavoured the ſame thing, but with that good effect, that the greateſt and the moſt conſiderable part of his Subjects were dutifully return'd to the Profeſſion of the Religion of their Fore-fathers. Having thus obſerved that the Characters of the Ancient Perſecutors, and that of the Modern, are ſo like; and that the pretence of their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution is the ſame; I intend to conſider in this place the Method the <hi>French</hi> King has taken to compaſs his deſign, that we may ſee if the Parallel between them is exact in all its parts.</p>
               <p n="1">1. We have ſeen in the firſt place, that the Perſecutors began their Perſecution againſt the Chriſtians by pulling down their Churches; and here we muſt again obſerve, that this <hi>French</hi> King began to perſecute the <hi>Hugonots</hi> by the very ſame method. 'Tis true it was not with ſuch Rage as the Heathens ſhewed on this occaſion; it was with ſome colourable appearance of Juſtice, which was ſtill worſe than an open Violence, becauſe the Proteſtants were obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to be at vaſt Charges to make good their Titles, and yet for all that they were afterwards Condemn'd, and 'tis no wonder indeed, ſince their Enemies were their Judges. In fine then, the moſt part of the Proteſtant Churches were pulled down under a frivolous pretence, <hi>viz.</hi> That they were eſtabliſhed againſt the Diſpoſition of the Edicts, or becauſe ſome <hi>Mahometans</hi> had been preſent in the Aſſemblies, which was prohibited by an Edict given in 1680.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:52644:8"/>
               <p n="2">2. The Chriſtians were declared during the <hi>Primitive Perſecutions,</hi> incapable of all Honours, and Publick Truſts, and Offices, as well Civil as Military; and the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants have been treated with the ſame Inhumanity by their Prince, which I am now to prove. <hi>Les Chambres de l'Edict,</hi> which were Soveraign Courts, compoſed of an equal number of Proteſtants, and <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> and to which the Cauſes of the Proteſtants were referred, were ſuppreſſed, and afterwards all the Inferior Judges of the Kingdom. In a word, all Civil Officers and Magiſtrates, that were Proteſtants, were turned by force out of their Imployments. The Military Officers were not, I confeſs, uſed with ſo much ſeverity, for there was no Declaration come forth againſt them; but however they were obliged to leave their Service, becauſe they could not hope to come to any great Preferment; the Office of a Captain being their greateſt reward, notwithſtanding their long, faithful, continued Services. To all thoſe Vexations, they added another no leſs cruel and unjuſt, the Proteſtants were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden in ſeveral Parts of the Kingdom to Exerciſe any Trade or Art, in order to take away from them all means of getting their Livelihood, and induce them to turn Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts. The King himſelf by a Declaration in 1680, prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited all the Proteſtants to practice the Art of Midwifry. What can be imagined more unjuſt and cruel than the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecurion of <hi>France?</hi> What, I ſay, more cruel and unjuſt can be imagined, than to deprive ſo many Magiſtrates of their Offices? What more cruel than to prohibit Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants the Exerciſe of the Natural Gifts God had endowed them with to get their Livelihood? And what more unjuſt and oppoſite to the Chriſtian Charity, than to throw ſo many Men into the loweſt Poverty, and force them to beg their Bread? And all this againſt the expreſs terms of the <hi>Edict</hi> of <hi>Nantes,</hi> where one may read the following words in the 27th Article, <hi>We declare the Proteſtants capable of all Imployments, Dignities, Offices, and Charges, whatever they be,</hi> &amp;c. and againſt the very Oath and Promiſe given by this <hi>French</hi> King.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:52644:8"/>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Lactantius</hi> has obſerved, That the Chriſtians were put out of the Protection of the Laws, that they might not ſue for Wrongs and Injuries done to them; and have not the Proteſtant, in <hi>France</hi> received the like Treatment from their King; their Judges and Magiſtrates being forced out of their places? So that they ſeldom obtained Juſtice; and the ſtrongeſt Argument their Parties uſed againſt them, was, <hi>That they were Hugonots,</hi> which was ſufficient to make them loſe their Cauſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. After all theſe Vexations and Perſecutions, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired them but very few <hi>Proſelites;</hi> the Perſecutors began at laſt to take off their Mask, and the Intendants of the Provinces at the head of the <hi>Booted Miſſionaries,</hi> required in the Kings Name, all the Proteſtants to abjure their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as the old Perſecutor, commanded all the Chriſtians to return to their Ancient Inſtitution. I will not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble my Reader with a thouſand inſtances of this nature, which I could give, but I cannot forbear mentioning what happened at <hi>Bergerac</hi> in <hi>Perigord,</hi> where I was by chance at that very time. 'Tis a pretty conſiderable Town, ſituated upon the River <hi>Dordoigne,</hi> and the moſt part of its Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants were Proteſtants; they had ſuffered in 1682, a great Perſecution, and with ſo much Courage and ſteady Reſolution, that only two <hi>Hugonots,</hi> as I was informed, did forſake their Religion; and that Church was look'd upon by the Perſecutors, as a neſt of Hereticks, and which was likely to make the gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt Reſiſtance, therefore they deſigned to attack it in an extraordinary manner. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis <hi>de Boufflers,</hi> Commander in chief of the <hi>French</hi> Kings Forces in <hi>Aquitaine,</hi> went with the <hi>Intendant,</hi> and two Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, at the head of five or ſix thouſand Men; they ſet out Guards round about the Town, and in the Streets, and no body was ſuffered to come out; and aftewards they called together the inhabitants into the Town-houſe, where the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendant made them a fine Speech. Becauſe the thing ſeemed to me very extraordinary, I went in among the Croud, and I heard the <hi>Intendant</hi> tell them among other things, <hi>That the King his Maſter being perſuaded of their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52644:9"/>in continuing thier Separation from the Church without any grounds, he was reſolved out of his Royal Mercy to reconcile them to her Holy Communion; and that therefore they muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther voluntarily renounce their Hereſy, or they ſhould be compelled to do it according to the precept of the Goſpel.</hi> One may eaſily gueſs what a cruel Stab theſe words were to the hearts of theſe poor Inhabitants; and yet with a noble Bravery they return'd him this Anſwer, <hi>That their Eſtates and Lives being in the power of the King, they were reſolved to undergo all manner of hardſhips as to them; but God alone being the Maſter of their Conſciences, they would rather ſuffer a thouſand Deaths, than renounce his true Religion which they profeſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. I have obſerved how the <hi>Primitive Perſecutors,</hi> ſeeing that notwithſtanding all their Perſecutions, the Chriſtians ſtill ſtood firm to their Rules, practiſed more and more upon them all manner of Cruelties; and <hi>Lactantius</hi> gives this following Deſcription of the horrid Puniſhments they condemned many Chriſtians to. They were, ſays he, firſt chained to a Poſt, then there was a gentle Fire ſet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Soles of their Feet, by which all the <hi>Callus</hi> of the Foot was ſhrivel'd up, till at laſt it fell off from the Bones; then <hi>Flambeaux</hi> were lighted and put out, and while they were not, clapt to all the parts of their Bodies, that ſo they might be tortured all over; and care was taken to keep them alive as long as was poſſible, by throwing cold Water on their Faces, and every now and then giving them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to cool and refreſh their Mouths, leſt otherwiſe the Violence of the Miſery they ſuffered, ſhould quite dry up their Throats, and ſo choak them. Thus their Sufferings were lengthned out whole days, till at laſt their Skin being quite conſumed by the Fire, it reached their Vitals, and then a great Fire was kindled, into which they were thrown, and ſo their Bodies were burnt to Aſhes, and their Bones that were not wholly deſtroyed, were gathered and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Powder, and then thrown into ſome River, or elſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sea. Truly the lively Picture of this horrid Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is very diſmal and hideous. And were I as Eloquent
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52644:9"/>as <hi>Lactantius,</hi> or at leaſt, capable of putting what Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Claude</hi> hath ſaid of the Sufferings of the <hi>French</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants into a graceful Turn in <hi>Engliſh.</hi> I would undertake to make as frightful a Portraicture as this of that famous Writer.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Infernal Miſſionnaries</hi> ſet on foot, ſays he, to convert the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants did with a thouſand Blaſphemies, and execrable Oaths, hang up Men and Women by their Hairs of their Head, or downwards by their Feet in the ſmoak of wet Hay, where they were almoſt choaked to Death; and when they had taken them down, and let them come a little to themſelves, if they would not then turn Papiſts, they hung them up again.</p>
               <p>They pinched their Beards off, and their Hairs of their Heads, till they had made an abſolute <hi>Depilation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They threw them into great Fires, and when they were half roaſted, took them up again, and tying them under the Arm-pits, dipped them in cold Water again and again, till they had made them promiſe to renounce their Hereſy. They tied up ſome others (like Criminals, who were to ſuffer the Rack) and then with a Funnel poured ſtrong Wines down their Throats, till its Vapours getting up into their heads had almoſt drowned their Reaſon, and then they asked them to be reconciled to the <hi>Church.</hi> They ſtrip'd them ſtark naked, and after a thouſand horrid Indignities, they ſtuck all their Bodies with Pins. They mangled others in a moſt ſtrange manner with Pen-knives; and their Inhumanity went ſo far, as to take them by the Noſe with hot Tongs, till they forced them to a compliance. They ſtruck others with Sticks, and when they were almoſt dead, carried them into the Churches, where their bare Preſence was taken for a formal Abjuration. They kept them from ſleeping for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or eight days together, either by throwing freſh Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter on their Faces, or by making a horrid Noiſe with Drums or Kettles. If they could find any Sick, they cauſed the Drums to be beat round their Beds, and ſo obliged thoſe miſerable Creatures to renounce their Religion. Sometimes they tied Parents and Husbands to Bed-poſts, and then would attempt to Raviſh their Daughters, and their Wives,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52644:10"/>before their faces. They pulled their Nails off their hands and Feet, which is the moſt acute and ſenſible Pain ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable; and if any of them died, they were drawn to the common Lay-ſtalls, and there eaten up by Dogs, and other Beaſts.</p>
               <p>I ſhould never have done, if I were to give in Retail an Account of all the Barbarities committed on the <hi>French</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants; therefore I will content my ſelf with theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, which I hope are ſufficient to prove, that I could make as gaſtly a Picture of the Perſecution of our Age, as <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> has done of that of the Primitive Chriſtians. But if this be not enough, I refer my Reader to a Book, called, <hi>The Complaints of the perſecuted Proteſtants in</hi> France, at which the <hi>French</hi> King was ſo offended, that at the deſire of his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter here at our Court, it was publikly burnt in the late King's time.</p>
               <p n="6">6. To make an exact Parallel between the Modern and Ancient Perſecutors, it remains only to inquire further, whether the <hi>Books of the Holy Scripture</hi> have not been burnt by the <hi>French</hi> King's orders, as well as by <hi>Maximians:</hi> But this I think will be out of queſtion, ſince we have here ſo many thouſand Witneſſes, who can all atteſt the truth of that horrid Impiety; for tho I have ſeen it with my own Eyes, yet I do not deſire to be believed upon my ſingle Word or Teſtimony.</p>
               <p>I have ſufficiently made out the Parallel I promiſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>French</hi> King, and the Perſecutors of the <hi>Primitive</hi> Church. I have ſhewed that they were alike in their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and in their Actions; that the pretences of their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution have been the ſame, and that they have made uſe of the like Methods to compaſs their deſign. I muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs obſerve, that thoſe Ancient Monſters cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to come up to the late heights of Cruelty, but muſt yield therein to the <hi>French</hi> King; they perſecuted the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, becauſe they denied their Gods to be Gods, and maintained that ſome of them had never been, and that the others were vicious Men, and dead long ago: <hi>We know,</hi> ſays <hi>Tertullian</hi> to them, <hi>where ſome of your Gods are buried.</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:52644:10"/>Beſides, they were not prohibited by the Laws of their Gods to be cruel towards the Chriſtians; but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, <hi>Lactantius</hi> obſerveth, That <hi>Apollo</hi> being conſulted by <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> adviſed him to perſecute them with the laſt Severity, which maketh their Perſecution a little excuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: But what can excuſe the <hi>French</hi> King's Cruelty? Do the Proteſtants deny the God the Papiſts worſhip, I mean the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, to be the true God? If they ſay with them, That the Son is dead for our Sins; do not they ſay alſo, That he <hi>roſe again from the dead?</hi> Had the <hi>French</hi> King been ſo canticus as <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> that is, had he conſulted the holy Word of his God, he would have ſeen how contrary the Meekneſs and Charity of that, is to his Cruelty and Perſuecution. And I dare ſay, that if he had conſulted <hi>Innocent</hi> the XI. who was to have been his God upon Earth; I doubt very much, whether he would have adviſed him to be ſo barbarous towards his own Subjects. I'll add but a Reflection about the Books of the Holy Scripture which have been burnt by the Ancient and Modern Perſecutorss; and I ſay, that the <hi>Maximians,</hi> the <hi>Diocleſians,</hi> &amp;c. looking upon thoſe Books as Impious and Blaſphemous againſt their Gods, they were leſs crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal in condemning them to the fire, than the <hi>French</hi> King, who, if he be a Chriſtian, cannot look upon the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Bibles without ſome Reſpect and Reverence, being the Law, and the Will of his God, notwithſtanding the few in conſiderable Alterations they pretend we have made in our Tranſlation.</p>
               <p>The Perſecution of the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants having been ſo viole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t as we have ſeen, according to this Vulgar Axiom, <hi>Nihil violentum eſt diuturnum;</hi> it ſhould not have laſted a very long time, and yet it hath continued ſome five and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years, or more, (but eſpecially ſince the late King <hi>Charles</hi>'s Death) without abating any thing of its Rigour and Cruelty. It was thought alſo, that the <hi>French</hi> King being ſo taken up in defending himſelf againſt ſo many Enemies, might have cool'd his Anger for a while; but we were mightily miſtaken, for he every day increaſes his Rage and Fury againſt them, becauſe he looks upon them as his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52644:11"/>neareſt, and ſo worſt Enemies, believing that after the many Perſecutions and Hardſhips he hath made them ſuffer, they would ſoon joyn with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in caſe of any Deſcent. Every new year affords new Barbarities, and eſpecially this; for the Proteſtants have been dealt with more ſeverely in all parts of <hi>France</hi> this laſt, than they had been the three or four years before. It ſeems however that the <hi>Lower Aquitaine</hi> has been the Scene of their greateſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanities; and a true Relation thereof being come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my hands, I am deſired to publiſh it, and as willing to gratiſy ſo reaſonable a Requeſt. The Account is as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>A Faithful Account of the Renewed Perſecution of the Proteſtants in <hi>Lower Aquitaine:</hi> Collected out of ſeveral Letters, written by known Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons from that Province; and taken from the Depoſition made by a Gentleman newly arrived from thoſe Parts, who for his Religion ſake has had his Houſe pulled down, and razed to the Ground, and himſelf hung up in Effigy.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAintefoy</hi> and <hi>Genſac</hi> are Two Towns ſcituated upon the River <hi>Dordoigne,</hi> and <hi>Duras</hi> upon the little River <hi>Drot.</hi> This laſt is not ſo conſiderable as the other Two, for the Number of the Inhabitants, but it is no leſs in all other points, being a <hi>Dutchy,</hi> and the principal ſeat of the Duke of <hi>Duras,</hi> Brother to the Earl of <hi>Feverſham. Saintefoy</hi> had, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the repealing of the Edict of <hi>Nants,</hi> a Church of about Three thouſand Communicants, <hi>Genſac</hi> Two thouſand, and <hi>Duras</hi> only but Five hundred, but theſe were the moſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the Town. Thoſe Churches, with the others, fell
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52644:11"/>under the Mercileſs violence of the Dragoons; and for three or four Years together, ſhewed a very weak fearfulneſs; but ſince that time, it hath pleaſed God, they have recovered their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, as many others have done in that Province, and have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied going to Maſs. Being however unſatisfied in their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and weary of being longer withhold from their ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Devotions of praying to God together, they made the laſt Year ſeveral Aſſemblies in ſome private Houſes; where they performed all the exerciſes of their Religion, with one of thoſe couragious Miniſters that were ſent thither to Preach <hi>und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r the Croſs.</hi> And they continued their Meetings for ſome time, but in a very peaceful way, and with a mind as far from all ſedition, as the Witneſſes againſt them have ſince teſtified and declar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d; though after this diſcovery they have been dealt with as Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals of <hi>State.</hi> The Aſſembly of <hi>Duras</hi> was the firſt diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered; whereupon Mr. <hi>'Duqueſne Lieutenant Criminal</hi> of <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>as</hi> was ſent thither by the Intendant of the Province. Many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations were brought in before that Magiſtrate, and War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants Iſſued out againſt the moſt conſiderable Inhabitants; who wiſely foreſeeing what was like then to beſal them, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to make their eſcape: Three men however were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily taken, <hi>viz.</hi> Meſſieurs <hi>Conſtans, Beſcete,</hi> and <hi>la Roche,</hi> who was formerly the Reader and Schoolmaſter of the ſaid Church, with Three Gentlewomen, <hi>viz.</hi> Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and <hi>Mary Gentillot,</hi> Siſters, and one Mrs. <hi>Barbote.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Six Priſoners were brought into the Priſon of the Town-houſe of <hi>Bordeaux,</hi> and thence into the Gaol of the Parliament; where that <hi>la Roche,</hi> being a fearful man in his Temper, was eaſily frighted by the Judges, inſomuch, that under promiſe of Pardon, he was prevail'd with to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover all thoſe who had been in thoſe Meetings: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſo many Warrants were iſſued out, that the Town of <hi>Duras</hi> was almoſt become a Deſert by the flight of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> who were to be ſeized. The Intendant, with the <hi>Seneſchal</hi> of <hi>Aquitaine,</hi> Condemned the ſaid <hi>Conſtans</hi> and <hi>Beſcete</hi> to the Gallies; the firſt for his Life, and the laſt for Five Years only: But before both of them were to make, as they call it, <hi>L'amende honnorable;</hi> the Three Women were Condemned to this laſt Puniſhment, To be
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52644:12"/>ſhaven by the Hangman, and afterwards ſhut up for their Lives in the Manufacture, which is a kind of Bridewell. Meſſieurs <hi>Conſtans,</hi> and <hi>Beſcete,</hi> made their <hi>Honourable Amend</hi> at <hi>Bordeance;</hi> but becauſe this Puniſhment is unknown here in <hi>England,</hi> I think it not amiſs to relate the manner of it. Theſe poor Gentlemen bare headed and bare feeted, and almoſt Naked, having but a courſe linnen Shirt upon their back, having beſides a Halter on their necks, a burning Torch in their hands, the Hangman at their heels, were lead in that Garb from the Jail of the Palace through the ſtreets as far as the Square of St. <hi>Andrews</hi> Church, which is as far, as from Charing-Croſs to Ludgate; the Hangman telling them, that he was to Hang them at his return. Notwithſtanding theſe hard uſages, and the rigors of the Seaſon; they ſhewed ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs an humble, modeſt, and chearful Conſtancy and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience; which made ſo great an impreſſion upon the very Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of their Religion, that they could not for bear their Tears, and ſome of them ſaid, they <hi>are called to Glorifie God by their Martyrdom.</hi> Mr. <hi>Conſtans</hi> ſeemed ſtill more firm than his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-ſufferer; for being asked by the Judges, Whether he had not been in thoſe unlawful Aſſemblies? He did not deny it, but anſwered undauntedly, That <hi>he had been there many times, and that he would go again if he could,</hi> which was the occaſion of one increaſing of his Puniſhment. I have ſaid, that the Judges had promiſed <hi>la Roche</hi> his pardon, and therefore he was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed.</p>
               <p>A little while after the taking of theſe Priſoners at <hi>Duras,</hi> ſeveral Perſons of <hi>Saintefoy</hi> and <hi>Genſac</hi> were ſeized for the ſame account, and the <hi>21ſt.</hi> of <hi>February</hi> laſt they were removed from the Priſons of thoſe places into the Jail at <hi>Bordeaux.</hi> Amongſt them were Monſieur <hi>Pages de Margueyron,</hi> and his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. He was a Gentleman very Judicious, Pious, and Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, mightily beloved by the People, and by the Perſons of Quality with whom he lived very honourably; he had but one Son, who being eſcaped from the Dragoons, was kill'd in <hi>Ireland</hi> in Their Majeſties Service, being an Officer in one of the <hi>French</hi> Regiments of Foot, Commanded by Brigadeer <hi>la Meloniere.</hi> His Lady had a great deal of Wit, Piety, Zeal, and Charity, and they were a mutual comfort one to the other,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52644:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>as long as they were together in the ſame Priſon; but though they were ſeparated about the time of their Jugment, that ſad affliction did not leſſen their Conſtancy. Nothing was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten to ſhake them, and they were tryed both with promiſes and threatnings, but always in main. This obliged their Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors to fall upon other methods, and knowing how dear Monſieur <hi>Margueyron</hi> was to his Wife, they endeavoured to abuſe her tenderneſ to win him. Therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e they promiſed her the life of her Husband, if ſhe would ſolli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him to renounce his Religion; but inſtead of doing it, ſhe ſent a Friend to ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate him to ſtand out firm, and not to bely the Character of a Chriſtian; adding withal, that ſhe ſhould certainly dye with Grief, if he had any weakneſs. A <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick, her Friend, being preſent, did blame her for ſo deſperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adviſing her H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>nd; but ſhe anſwered him <hi>That ſhe would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſee her Husband (tho very dear to her) burning in a fire, than hear that he had been ſo weak, as to change his Religion.</hi> As ſoon as her Husband was condemned, ſhe was told of it, and that he likewiſe had notice to prepare for it; thereupon ſhe inquired only, how he had received that advice; and hearing that it was with a great deal of Courage, and with an undaunted ſirmneſs, ſhe ſhewed an extream Joy, and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on her Knees, returned her thanks to the Almighty, beſeeching him with a Chriſtian fervency, to inflame more and more his Reſignation and Courage to the very end of his Life. She declared beſides. <hi>That her Tears did not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from any natural Weakneſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> only from a deep Sorrow, that God had not thought her worthy to ſuffer for his Glory unto Blood, and to be the Fellow ſufferer of her Husband, that ſhe would have lodged on it as a great happineſs to her, had we been to dye with him, for the Glory of him who had given his Life for their Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; that nevertheleſs ſhe was ſatisfied to giveth the Saviour of her Soul the Life of the Husband he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> given her for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of her own; knowing that if they were ſeparated for a while, they ſhould be rejoyned for ever in the fellowſhip of the Glory, where they ſhould neither have Enemies to four, nor Tribulation to undergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Husband on his ſide ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ewed the Conſtancy and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation of a Marter, and anſwered ſtoutly, <hi>That with God's Grace he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to fight, and to ſtand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:52644:13"/>
               <p>The Judges were not a little perplexed at this Gentlemans Tryal, becauſe they were told, that he was not to dye, the King's Declaration condemning to death only thoſe that were taken in the Fact, that is, in the Aſſemblies, and not thoſe who, as Monſieur <hi>Margueyron,</hi> were indicted for having been there. The matter was plain, and the Judges had nothing to ſay againſt it, but on the contrary they confeſſed, <hi>That ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Written-law be was not to dye; but that according to the Oral Order they had received thereupon, and which was ſtronger than the Law it ſelf, he ought to ſuffer death.</hi> Truly the Judges were in the right, to ſpeak of that <hi>Oral Order,</hi> for we are certainly informed, that he was condemned by an expreſs Order of the King's Council.</p>
               <p>The very morning he was removed from <hi>Bordeaux</hi> to <hi>Sainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foy,</hi> the place of his Execution, all devout Perſons gave him a viſit in the Priſon, and we are told, that many Letters could hardly contain the good things he told them, as to the Profeſſion of the Chriſtian Religion, and as to his Reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to the Will of God. They were ſo much affected with his admirable Diſcourſes, and ſo paſſionately moved by his ſmiling Countenance, that none could ſpeak a word to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort or incourage him; but truly he had no need of it, having had the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> for his Comforter to his end. When he was brought out of the Priſon of <hi>Bordeaux,</hi> there was above two thouſand Perſons about him, ſome weeping, ſome admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his firm and chearful Countenance, and ſome others ſaying, <hi>See how he out-braves the King with his ſmiling Face.</hi> A <hi>Prieſt</hi> obſerving his placid looks under the heavineſs of his Chains, could not forbear his Tears, nor ſaying to thoſe that were about him, <hi>The</hi> Hugonots <hi>can boaſt that they have a Martyr in him.</hi> And indeed, had not that Gentleman and his Lady ſhewed ſuch Conſtancy and Patience, they would have degenerated from the Piety of their Anceſtors, who have been always zealous<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for their Religion, and of whom two have ſuffered Martyrdom formerly, as may be ſeen in the <hi>French</hi> Martyrology.</p>
               <p>That Glorious Confeſſor going out of his Priſon, gave his Bleſſing to all he met in his way, ſaying to thoſe he ſaw com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionately weeping for his Sufferings, <hi>Don't weep for me, but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52644:13"/>Weep for your ſelves, and take care to live better hereafter, than you have done hitherto;</hi> adding, That his life was not at all dear to him, provided he could run out his Race with Joy, as he hoped he ſhould do. Tho his Chains were exceeding heavy, yet one might ſee in his face a pleaſant chearfulneſs, like that we may obſerve in other men when they are advanc'd to ſome high and noble Dignity. The Three Gentlewomen of <hi>Duras,</hi> we before ſpoke of, who were Condemned to make their <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Amand</hi> in their own Town, and in the ſight of their Relations; (that ſo their Puniſhment might appear the more infamous) were brought out of Jail, at the ſame time with <hi>Monſieur Margueyron,</hi> being faſtned one to another, and ſent along with him to <hi>Saintefoy,</hi> attended by ſeveral Bailiffs, and the Hangman: Their deſign in this was to frighten thoſe Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant and Chriſtian Souls from their firſt Conſtancy, by making them ſpectators of the Death and Sufferings of that Gracious Martyr; but God be praiſed, they were rather the more ſtrengthned by what thoſe Miſcreants thought would be ſo frightful a ſpectacle to them, than any ways terrified, as we ſhall ſee in the ſequel of this Relation.</p>
               <p>Several Perſons went from <hi>Bordeaux</hi> to <hi>Saintefoy,</hi> to be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the undaunted Courage and Conſtancy of our n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w-going to be gloryſied Saint, and to ſtrengthen themſelves by his holy Exhortations, as well as by his Example. About an hour before his Death, he ſent for his Daughters and near Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and acquainted them with ſeveral things they knew not of; he commanded them above all things, to beſtow as much of his Eſtate as they could to the Poor; he exhorted them to ſtand in the profeſſion of the Truth, for which he was joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully going to reſign his life; and afterwards he deſired an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance of his to let his Informer know, that he did hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forgive him, and would dye his Friend. He was Executed at <hi>Saintefoy</hi> in the publick place, on <hi>Saturday</hi> the <hi>26th.</hi> of <hi>April</hi> laſt, <hi>New-ſtile.</hi> Though it was the Market-day, the Shops and the Windows were ſhut up, and there was no body to be ſeen in the Streets but a croud of poor ſorrowful People, <hi>ſaying, What ſhall we do? What will become of us? We loſe in this Great Good man our Protector and Father.</hi> The Gallows was incompaſſed round with a Troop of Horſe, and a Company of Foot, yet even thoſe could not hinder a croud of Poor people getting
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52644:14"/>near it, (and amongſt them two Gentltmen of <hi>Bordeaux</hi> in diſguiſe) on purpoſe to hear the laſt dying Speech of our Martyr, who was brought thither with the three before-mentioned Gentle-women; and no ſooner was he got upon the Ladder, than he ſaid, <hi>This is Jacob</hi>'s <hi>ladder, by which I am aſcending to Heaven.</hi> He had a mind to make a Speech to the People, but no ſooner did he begin to open his Mouth, but the Trumpets and Drums began to ſound, that his words might not be heard: Thereupen he deſired a ſhort ceſſation, wherein to make his Prayers to God, but was allowed none, but was immediately turn'd off the Ladder, pronouncing theſe words of the Royal <hi>Pſalmiſt, Into thine hands I commit my ſpirit; for thou haſt redeemed me, O Lord God of truth,</hi> Pſal. 31. v. 5. His Body was left upon the Gallows till the <hi>Sunday</hi> following at Night, and then at the requeſt of the Inhabitants, delivered to one of his Farmers, who Buried it in a private place. The ſame day he was Executed, his houſe was Levelled to the ground, and the materials of it given to the Prieſt of the Pariſh to inlarge his Church with, and his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Eſtates have been ſeized for the paying of 6000. Livers, to which the charges or Penalties of his Trial amounted. Thus died that Brave and Religious Martyr, without ſhewing any weakneſs, or ſo much as Anger at his Perſecutors; but on the contrary, ſuch a meekneſs and unſhaken conſtancy, that the Papiſts themſelves were heard to ſay, That if any man of their Religion had led ſo Pious a life, as Monſieur <hi>Margueyron</hi> had done, and had dyed in ſo Chriſtian a manner, he would be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly Canonized.</p>
               <p>When the ſad News of his death was brought to his Wife, ſhe ſhewed ſomewhat more than a manly Courage, it being without any ſign at all of Human weakneſs. She immediately returned her devout Thanks to God, for the great ſteadineſs of Reſolution he had given to her Husband, and ſaid to thoſe about her, <hi>He is now very happy, for he reſteth from his Labours.</hi> She was Condemned likewiſe to aſſiſt at her Husband's Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to be ſhaven by the Hangman, and afterwards confined for her life in the <hi>Manufacture</hi> of <hi>Bordeaux;</hi> but either they thought it would be too Cruel in them to let her ſee the Tragical end of her Husband, or rather they ſeared by her Bravery of Soul ſhe would incourage him the more, and too much work upon the Peoples affections; they left her in the Priſon of <hi>Bordeaux</hi> till the Execution of her Husband was over.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:52644:14"/>
               <p>The three Gentlewomen that came along with him, having ſeen Monſieur <hi>Margueyron</hi>'s Death without being in the leaſt ſhaken, contrary to their Perſecutor's expectation, were brought from <hi>Saintefoy</hi> to <hi>Duras,</hi> where they made their <hi>Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Amand</hi> on the 28th. of the ſaid Month of <hi>April,</hi> being the Market-day at that place: They had never appeared in their lives ſo chearful, nor had their faces ever been ſo charming, as they ſeemed then in that frightful Garb; the moanful beams of the burning Torch they carried in their hands, did as it were increaſe the natural brightneſs of their Eyes; and the wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Halter they had on their necks, was a much more fine and glorious ſight, than a Pearl or Diamond Necklace. We have told you in the beginning of this Relation, that ſeveral Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of <hi>Duras</hi> who had been Indicted, had made their Eſcapes; they were Summoned, but not having appeared, they were Condemned by Out-lawry to be Hang'd, and to be Hang'd im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately in <hi>Effigie,</hi> till they could be found; inſomuch, that on that very day thoſe Gentlewomen Glorified God by their Sufferings at <hi>Duras,</hi> Four Gentlemen and a Gentlewoman were Hang'd up in <hi>Effigie, viz.</hi> Monſieur <hi>Fontanote</hi> and his Wife, Monſieur <hi>Peynau,</hi> Advocate in the Court of Parliament, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Micheau</hi> a Merchant, and Monſieur <hi>de Peyferier</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who is newly arrived here in <hi>England,</hi> and from whom we have ſome particulars of this Relation; and the ſame day alſo his houſe, in which they uſed to have their Religious Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, was pulled down. The Three Gentlewomen were brought back to <hi>Bordeaux,</hi> and being ſhaven by the Hangman, they were ſhut up in the <hi>Manufacture,</hi> where they ſhew the like Patience, Conſtancy, and Chearfulneſs, as they did in their former Sufferings.</p>
               <p>The Perſecutors have been no leſs rigorous to the Church of <hi>Genſac,</hi> than to the two former. Many Perſons were Indicted, and one of them called <hi>John de Lande,</hi> being taken, has been ſent to the Gallies for Three Years. Seven others that are ſled, have been Condemned by Out-lawry to be hang'd, amongſt whom are theſe Gentlemen, <hi>Meſſieurs Belleveue de Durege, de Bellefonds, de Vialle, and Peyriere de Gentillot,</hi> whoſe Houſes have been pulled down.</p>
               <p>Every Age of Chriſtianity has found by experience, that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52644:15"/>the Blood of the Martyrs is the ſeed of the Church; and we hear alſo that comfortable truth upon this occaſion: We are told that the Death of Monſieur <hi>Margueyron,</hi> together with the generous Sufferings of thoſe Confeſſors we have already ſpoken of, has awakened and enlivened the ſleeping zeal of many People, inſomuch that we are aſſured, that ſeveral other Perſons would joyfully Sacrifice their lives, rather than fall again into their former weakneſs. Several Perſons of <hi>Nerac,</hi> and of <hi>Lygoules</hi> near <hi>Bergerac</hi> are alſo Perſecuted, and ſome taken, though ſentence has not been pronounc'd againſt them, for ought we can yet learn; and we are informed by the laſt publick accounts, that the Perſecution continneth there with a very great fury, as well as in all other Provinces of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would here put an end to this Diſcourſe, but that I promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to make ſome few Reflections upon the unreaſonable fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a certain hot Party amongſt us for the <hi>French</hi> King; tho they at the ſame time pretend to be both true <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> and good Proteſtants. Indeed their proceedings are ſo odd and extravagant, that future Ages will hardly believe what we ſee with our own Eyes. Theſe Gentlemen would fain perſwade the World, that the Perſecutions in <hi>France</hi> have not been ſo violent as we have been informed, and that the <hi>French</hi> King hath now chang'd his mind, and is become another man: But what can be more idle, ridiculous, and impertinent, than this ſtuff of theirs? Would they with a Brazen brow, give the lye to ſo many Thouſands of Witneſſes, and to our own eyes too? But what new varniſh can they find to put upon this laſt Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution? Truly if the <hi>French</hi> King hath now changed his mind, he muſt have been exceeding violent indeed, ſince the very dregs of his Fury are ſtill ſo terrible; For what more Cruel can be imagined, than to put a Gentleman to a vile and infamous death; to ſend ſo many others to the Gallies, and to condemn others to ſhameful Puniſhment, upon the bare pretence that they have met together to Pray to God, notwithſtanding his prohibition? If ſo hard treatment may not be call'd a Perſecution, I do not know then what may deſerve that name: and on the contrary, if this be meekneſs and gentleneſs, I cannot imagine what that is which we call Inhumanity.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:52644:15"/>
               <p>I would beg leave to ask our Murmurers only two queſtions. 1. How is it poſſible that a Tyrant, who has ſo cruelly perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted the Proteſtants in his own Kingdom; who has pulled down ſo many of their Churches, put to death ſo many men upon account of Religion only; who, further yet, boaſts, That he himſelf hath almoſt rooted out the Hereſie; and who ſtill continues his Rage and Fury againſt all the Proteſtants that are found in his Dominions; I ſay, How is it poſſible, that ſuch a man can ever be the Protector of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as our Grumbling Crew call him? Perhaps they will anſwer, That the <hi>French Hugonots</hi> have not been uſed with ſo much ſeverity upon the account of their Religion merely, but becauſe the <hi>French</hi> King found them dangerous to his Grandure and his State, having ſtrong ſuſpicions of their Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity; but let them prove what they ſay: I would fain know what Publick Act or Declaration they can inſtance in; and whether they have any Witneſſes that will ſay, the <hi>Booted-Miſſionaries</hi> have ever required from the <hi>Hugonots</hi> a greater Teſt of their Fidelity, than they had before, but only their forcing them to go to Maſs. Every body knows, that this <hi>French</hi> King owes his Crown to thoſe very Proteſtants he has ſo cruelly uſed; and conſequently, that their Fidelity could not be in the leaſt called into queſtion. But if the <hi>French</hi> King aimed not at the extirpation of the Proteſtant Religion, why doth he ſay in his Letters and Memorials againſt the <hi>Emperor</hi> and the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> that it was his intention? Why hath he deſtroyed the Churches of <hi>Orange,</hi> and forc'd his Majeſty's Subjects, as well as his own, to forſake their Religion, and to go to Maſs? And why hath he compelled the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> 10 deſtroy the <hi>Vaudcis,</hi> as his Royal Highneſs has publickly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared? The <hi>French</hi> King having then declared War againſt all the Proteſtants of the World, I thought the Church of <hi>England</hi> had not been excepted; and I was induced to that belief, by the Meaſures the late King had taken with him, ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually to deſtroy it; but being now aſſured by ſome, that he is the <hi>Protector</hi> of it, I am ſurprized at ſuch a wonderful Change; and this is the firſt <hi>Phoenomenon,</hi> the Solution of which I humbly deſire of our Learned Mutmurers.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:52644:16"/>
               <p>I ask, <hi>2dly.</hi> If it be poſſible, that a true <hi>Engliſh-man,</hi> that is, one living free under Their Majeſties moſt Gracious Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and making uſe of his right Reaſon, can wiſh a Tyrant for his King; an Oppreſſor, who has made his Subjects the moſt miſerable Wretches and Slaves in the world, tho In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of one of the moſt plentiful Countries of the earth; who ſucks their very blood and marrow from them, to ſatisfie his vaſt Ambition, or his impure Luſts and Pleaſures, and who ſacrifices them to his leaſt Intereſt or Vanity: The Enemy of Mankind, the Invader of his Neighbours: A Prince, if I may call him ſo, <hi>who has ever yet ſcorned to be a ſlave to his Oaths or Treaties; and on whom, the Religion be profeſſes, and all that is ſacred amongſt men, has no manner of Force or Power;</hi> to uſe the very words of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> in his Letter to the Pope. In a word, If it be poſſible for an <hi>Engliſh-man,</hi> who loves the Intereſt of his Nation, to wiſh for a man of the Character of this <hi>French</hi> King, to be his Abſolute Lord and Maſter?</p>
               <p>Till theſe Gentlemen will be pleaſed to anſwer me theſe two queſtions, I ſhall make bold to deliver my own thoughts upon them: And as to the firſt, I ſay, That the <hi>French</hi> King is not the <hi>Protector</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and that his Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters who give him that magnificent Title, prevaricate, and make uſe of ſome equivocation; for they muſt mean another Church far different from that here eſtabliſhed by the Laws of this Kingdom. Ours needs no other Protection, than that of Their Majeſties; and ſure I am, the Gentlemen I ſpeak of, are Papiſts in their hearts, notwithſtanding their ſo much affected outward ſhew of Proteſtantiſm, if they have any Religion at all. As to the ſecond Query, <hi>If it be poſſible for an Engliſh-man who loveth the true Intereſt of his Nation, to wiſh his Maſter might be a man of the Character of this</hi> French <hi>King?</hi> I anſwer, <hi>No:</hi> And therefore by the reaſons contained in the Query, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That the Murmurers are either Fools, or Enemies of this Countrey: Now to ſay they are the former, I confeſs it would ſeem a little too hard a Cenſure, and I ſhould wrong ſeveral of them, whom I know to be men of Parts. They are ſo fond of themſelves, that ſure I am, they would much rather be called <hi>Enemies</hi> to this Nation. And tho Complaiſance is oppoſite to my temper, yet for their ſakes I muſt upon this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52644:16"/>force my natural inclination, and agree with them, that this laſt Character is more ſuitable to their proceedings, than that of <hi>Fools.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having given an exact Parallel between the Ancient and Modern Perſecutors, my Deſign would be imperfect, ſhould I omit ſaying ſomething of the Tragick Death that common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attends the Enemies of the Church. God has in all ages made manifeſt the ſevere Judgments he exerciſes upon them. The Relation of the Deaths of the <hi>Primitive Perſecutors,</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Lactantius,</hi> which I have ſo often quoted, is ſo frightful, that the conſideration of their miſerable end, ought, one would think, to deter any man from Perſecuting for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and had the <hi>French</hi> King but reflected upon their Fate, and the Tragick Deaths of his own Anceſtors, I doubt very much whether he would have taken ſo dangerous a courſe. King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> who had ſworn to ſee <hi>Ann Dubourg</hi> a Proteſtant, burning at the ſtake, received a mortal wound in one of his eyes a few days before, from the Earl of <hi>Montgomery,</hi> of which he dyed 11 days after. <hi>Francis</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> who was very ſevere upon the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> dyed ſuddenly. <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>9th.</hi> who cauſed the ſaid <hi>Hugonots</hi> to be ſo barbarouſly murthered at the Bloody and Memorable Maſſacre at <hi>Paris,</hi> at laſt drowned himſelf in his own blood. <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>3d.</hi> no leſs cruel than his Brother, was killed by a <hi>Monk. Henry</hi> the <hi>4th.</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> to turn Papiſt, and withal a Bigot, was firſt wounded by a Diſciple of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards murdered in his own Coach, and in his chief City. And <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>13th.</hi> having endeavoured to extirpate the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, died miſerably, (as ſome ſay), being eaten up by Vermin. <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>14th.</hi> is not yet dead, and ſo I cannot tell what will be his ſate; but I would adviſe him to conſider the dreadful Death of <hi>Galerius Maximian;</hi> he was viſited by God with an Ulcer in his ſecret Parts, and dyed afterwards in a moſt miſerable manner. The <hi>French</hi> King is extremely like to that Ancient Perſecutor, let him fear leſt his <hi>Fiſtula</hi> does not preſage to him the ſame Fate.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:52644:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed for, and Sold by <hi>Richard Baldwin.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>EUrope's Chains Broke;</hi> Or, a Sure and Speedy <hi>Project</hi> to Reſcue <hi>Her</hi> from the Preſent <hi>Uſurpations</hi> of the Tyrant of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtianiſſimus Chriſtianandus.</hi> Or, Reaſon for the Reduction of <hi>France</hi> to a more <hi>Chriſtian State</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> By <hi>Marchimam Needham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Truth brought to Light.</hi> Or, the Hiſtory of the firſt Fourteen Years of King <hi>James</hi> the <hi>I.</hi> In Four Parts. <hi>I.</hi> The Happy State of <hi>England</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t His Majeſty's Entrance; The Corruption of it afterwards. With the Riſe of Particular Favourites, and the Diviſions between This and other States abroad. <hi>II.</hi> The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce betwixt the Lady <hi>Frances Howard</hi> and <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> before the King's Delegates, authorized under the King's Broad Seal. As alſo the Arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Sir <hi>Jervis Yelvis,</hi> Lieutenant of the Tower, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> about the Murther of Sir. <hi>Thomas Overbury,</hi> with all Proceedings thereupon, and the King's Grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pardon and Favour to the Counteſs. <hi>III.</hi> A Declaration of His Majeſty's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue ſince he came to the Crown of <hi>England.</hi> With the Annual Iſſues, Gifts, Penſions, and Extraordinary Disburſments, <hi>IV.</hi> The Commiſſions and Warrants for the Burning of two Hereticks, newly revived, with two Pardons, one for <hi>Theophilus Higgons,</hi> the other for Sir <hi>Euſtate Hart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A True Relation of the <hi>Cruelties</hi> and <hi>Barbarities</hi> of the <hi>French,</hi> upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Priſoners of War; being a Journal of their Travels from <hi>Dinant</hi> in <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany,</hi> to <hi>Thoulon</hi> in <hi>Provence:</hi> And back again. With a Deſcription of the Situation, and Fortifications of all the Eminent Towns upon the Road, and their Diſtance. Of their Priſons and Hoſpitals, and the Number of the Men that died under their Cruelty: With the Names of many of them, and the Places of their Deaths and Burials: With an Account of the great Charity and Sufferings of the Poor Proteſtants of <hi>France:</hi> And other Material Things that hapned upon the Way. Fathfully and Impartially performed by <hi>Richard Strutton,</hi> being an Eye-Witneſs, and a Fellow Sufferer.</p>
            <p>A Project of a Deſcent upon <hi>France,</hi> by a Perſon of Quality.</p>
            <p>A New, Plain, Short, and Compleat <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Engliſh Grammar;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Learner may attain in few Months to Speak and Write <hi>French</hi> Correctly, as they do now in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> and wherein all that is Dark, Superflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and Deficient in other <hi>Grammars,</hi> is Plain, Short and Methodically ſupplied. Alſo very uſeful to Strangers, that are deſirous to learn the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue; For whoſe ſake is added a ſhort, but very exact <hi>Engliſh Grammar.</hi> The Second Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by <hi>Peter Berault.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
